General Administration Records UA058
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
General Administration Records
1910 -- 1990
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Miller, Russell E.
Human Resources
Health Services
UA058
9.7 Linear Feet 13 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into one series: Unprocessed accessions.
Custodial History
This collection was compiled by Russell Miller. Some materials may have been removed to form their own collections.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains files and records pertaining to housing, health services, personnel, scholarships, and accounting, as well as correspondence and building plans for the Tufts Administration Building.
Biographical / Historical
Russell Elliott Miller was a Professor of History, University Historian and Archivist of Tufts University, and author of "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts College from 1852 to 1952" and the second volume "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts University since 1952." He was born in Bloomington, Minnesota, on April 25, 1916, to one of the last pioneer families in the Minnesota prairie. His mother spoke Dakota Sioux, which she had learned as a child. He received a B.A. in Education in 1937 and an M.A. in political science in 1939, both from the University of Florida at Gainesville. From 1942 to 1946, he served in the Army Air Corps as an enlisted man, rising to the rank of technical sergeant. Initially with personnel and classification, he was finally assigned to the historical section (intelligence) at the headquarters of the troop carrier command. In 1948 he earned a Master of Arts in history from Princeton University and came to Tufts that same year.
In 1952 he received a PhD from Princeton, and in 1964 Tufts appointed him Professor of History and University Historian and archivist. He taught courses ranging from the history of western civilization to the history of the American frontier. In 1966, he published "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts College from 1852 to 1952." That year he received the Distinguished Service Award from the Tufts Alumni Association and became an honorary member of Phi Beta Kappa. In 1975 he became the Walter S. Dickson Professor of English and American History and chaired the Department of History from then until 1980. He was voted Emeritus Professor of English and American History in 1981 and received an honorary Doctor of Letters degree in 1983. In 1986, he completed the second volume of Tufts history, "Light on the Hill II, A History of Tufts University since 1952."
Conditions Governing Access
University records are closed for 20 years from the date of their creation. Records older than 20 years that do not pertain to student education, staff and faculty employment and Board of Trustees records are open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Facilities; Employment and Human Resources; Curriculum and Instruction -- Scholarships, Fellowships, Awards
- Additional accessions, 1910 -- 1990; UA058.001
  - General Administration: Housing - including Dormitories, 1970 -- 1985; UA058-001 (Box data_value_missing_464b2eedf7bede247ed3c50e1ce5ff59, Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    20 years from date of creation.
  - General Administration: Financial Aid - Health Services, 1915 -- 1990; UA058-002 (Box data_value_missing_708bef00cc9e7b14cbf2d8ceb254a824, Box 2)
  - General Administration: Department of Human Resources, Personnel (staff) - Union, 1915 -- 1990; UA058-003 (Box data_value_missing_708bef00cc9e7b14cbf2d8ceb254a824, Box 3)
  - General Administration: Scholarships, 1910 -- 1990; UA058-004 (Box data_value_missing_708bef00cc9e7b14cbf2d8ceb254a824, Box 4)
  - General Administration: Accounting-Admissions, 1910 -- 1990; UA058-005 (Box data_value_missing_708bef00cc9e7b14cbf2d8ceb254a824, Box 5)
  - General Administration: Center for Enviromental Management, 1980 -- 1990; UA058-006 (Box data_value_missing_708bef00cc9e7b14cbf2d8ceb254a824, Box 6)
  - General Administration: Tufts Refugee Committee (World War II), 1940 -- 1950; UA058-007 (Box data_value_missing_708bef00cc9e7b14cbf2d8ceb254a824, Box 7)
  - General Administration: TAB, Western Executive Committee, 1960 -- 1985; UA058-009 (Box data_value_missing_708bef00cc9e7b14cbf2d8ceb254a824, Box 8)
  - General Administration: An Appraisal of Tufts University, 1960 -- 1985; UA058-010 (Box data_value_missing_708bef00cc9e7b14cbf2d8ceb254a824, Box 9)
  - General Administration: Dean A and S, Boston Technical School, Long-Range Planning, Center for Material Research, 1960 -- 1985; UA058-011 (Box data_value_missing_fbf4dd39c66d9ea10d78ba01609e3d63, Box 10)
  - General Administration: Scholarships, Fellowships, Prizes, Grants-in-Aid, 1960 -- 1985; UA058-012 (Box data_value_missing_fbf4dd39c66d9ea10d78ba01609e3d63, Box 11)
    Scope and Contents
    Scholarships named on folder labels: Bennett/Amer. Smelting and Refining Co.; William J. Bennett; Bragg; E. I. Dupont de Nemours & Co.; Fred M. Ellis; F. O. Hall Memorial; Charles Hayden Memorial; Hodgdon Fellowship; Michael T. Kelliher; Frank Merritt; Travelli Fund - Harold W. Davie; Lucius R. Paige; Lucy H. Stowe; Travelli; Vanderhoof; Wendell Phillips Memorial; Wilkinson; American Optical Co. - Mead; U.S. Steel Foundation, Inc.; deFlorez Prize in Human Engineering; Percival Clement Wood Prize
  - General Administration: V.P., Controller - Veterans Guidance Center, 1960 -- 1985; UA058-013 (Box data_value_missing_fbf4dd39c66d9ea10d78ba01609e3d63, Box 12)
  - General Administration: Departments/Offices, 1960 -- 1985; UA058-014 (Box data_value_missing_fbf4dd39c66d9ea10d78ba01609e3d63, Box 13)